Good morning. Today's דף daf is צדי דלת. tzadi dalet. We have
started הגוזל עצים, Hagozel Etzim, the last two פרקים prakim in the
בבא קמא Bava Kamma are הגוזל, Hagozel, some call it הגוזל קמא,
Hagozel Kamma, הגוזל בתרא, Hagozel Batra, and the ארבעה וחמישה, arba'ah v'chamisha,
as contrasted to the seventh פרק perek which was about גנבה gneiva
and we've been focusing a lot and will continue to focus today
on the aspects of שינויים, shinuyim, and when something changes, it, the
גזלן gazlan takes possession of it. And as yesterday some people were
noting even after the שיעור shiur that, didn't we discuss this a
while ago? And the answer is yes, that was the whole פרק
perek about גנבה gneiva in the seventh פרק. perek. So exactly why
these פרקים prakim are different and why the conversations don't seem to
be intersecting with one another, although they do seem to be parallel
to one another, is definitely a good question. But with that in
mind, the משנה mishna talked about making a שינוי shinuy and that
you take, the גזלן gazlan takes possession, and the גמרא Gemara talked
about two types of שינוי: shinuy: one that can be
reversed, can be חוזר לברייתו, chozer l'vriyaso, and one that cannot. And
the question was, as to one that can be חוזר לברייתו, chozer
l'vriyaso, does that work even on a דאורייתא d'Oraisa plane or does
that work only דרבנן? d'Rabanan? Okay, so now we pick up with
אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, no, one minute, yes, where are we? אמר
אביי, Amar Abaye, was that it? No, I think it was before
that. It was before that. Okay. הכי יש לומר. Hachi yesh lomar.
Right. Oh so
we have a little to catch up. It's about twenty lines from
the bottom, it's right before the little אלף aleph in parentheses. Okay,
so we had a discussion about רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that, that
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon said that, that if you whiten off wool,
whether that's considered to be a קניין kinyan or not. So there
was a question here because what was
it?
Hold on. Okay, right. That our משנה mishna says that whitening it,
or the ברייתא braisa says whitening it is a שינוי, shinuy, and
we have the case by ראשית הגז Reishis HaGez which said whitening
it was not a שינוי. shinuy. So which is it? So אביי
Abaye said that there's a, that's a debate of רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon and the
רבנן, Rabanan, because רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon basically says that after you
whiten something, it is a שינוי shinuy and the רבנן Rabanan say
that it's not a שינוי. shinuy. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
continues with this: הכי יש לומר, Hachi yesh lomar, צבע לדרבי שמעון
לא הוי שינוי. tzeva le-Rabbi Shimon lo havei shinuy. One minute. How
could רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon say whitening is a שינוי? shinuy? That's
the debate between רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and the רבנן, Rabanan, that
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says whitening is a שינוי shinuy and the
רבנן Rabanan say that it's not. I'm going to show you רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon says that even coloring something, even dyeing something is
not a שינוי. shinuy. ליבון הוי שינוי? Libun havei shinuy? So how
could he be saying in this case there by ראשית הגז Reishis
HaGez that whitening is? And here we have another case by ראשית
הגז Reishis HaGez itself, you can't even say it's a difference based
on the categories of
הלכה. halacha. דתניא: De-tanya: גזז ראשון ראשון וצבעו, gazaz rishon rishon u'tzeva'o,
as you're shearing it you are, you're dyeing the wool, גזז ראשון
ראשון וטואו, gazaz rishon rishon u'tevao, as you're shearing it you're, you
know, spinning the wool, גזז ראשון ראשון וארגו, gazaz rishon rishon v'argo,
or as you're doing it you're like weaving the wool, אין מצטרף.
ein mitztaref. So the fact that you've done something with the wool
makes it that it's no, that it's considered different and it doesn't
combine with the wool that you shear from the other sheep to
become the requisite amount to be obligated in giving the gift of
the shearings to the כהן. kohen.
You're supposed to give them just raw wool.
Right. רבי שמעון יהודה אומר Rabbi Shimon Yehudah omer משום רבי שמעון.
mishum Rabbi Shimon. But here anyway we're talking about preventing it from
being obligated as opposed to changing it after you've become obligated.
רבי שמעון יהודה אומר Rabbi Shimon Yehudah omer משום רבי שמעון, mishum
Rabbi Shimon, some say רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is רבי שמעון בן
יוחאי, Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai, וצבעו מצטרף. u'tzeva'o mitztaref. Even after you've
dyed it, it still combines. So how in one case of ראשית
הגז Reishis HaGez could רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon say that if you
whiten it,
it's a שינוי shinuy and it doesn't combine and by dyeing it
he says it does combine? Like it seems it should be the
exact opposite. Dyeing you add something, whitening you clean it, you beat
it or whatever, maybe we discussed adding sulfur. But how could that
be? So the גמרא Gemara says אמר אביי לא קשיא. Amar Abaye
lo kashya. הא רבנן אליבא דרבי שמעון והא רבי שמעון יהודה אליבא
דרבי שמעון. Ha Rabanan aliba d'Rabbi Shimon v'Ha Rabbi Shimon Yehudah aliba
d'Rabbi Shimon. There's a debate what רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon's position is.
I mean it is a קשיא, kashya, but the point is fine,
there're contradictory positions, there're two traditions what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon said.
רבא אמר לעולם לא פליגי רבנן עליבא דרבי שמעון יהודה. Rava amar
l'olam lo pligi Rabanan aliba d'Rabbi Shimon Yehudah. No, actually the רבנן
Rabanan who argue about whitening and say, do not argue with the
רבי שמעון יהודה Rabbi Shimon Yehudah when it comes to dyeing. Why
is that? ושאני צבע דהוי ויכול להחזירו על ידי צפה. v'shani tzeva
d'havei v'yachol lehachziro al yedei tzafa. Yes, actually dyeing is less of
a שינוי shinuy than whitening, especially if you think of whitening as
bleaching. The גמרא Gemara discussed the use of sulfur before about whitening.
I don't know if sulfur has the same effect, I don't know
exactly how bleach works. But anyway, right, if you dye something a
color, maybe you can, the think that you can remove the color.
It's an additive. So, Charlie's shaking his head. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara
says it's quite possible that there's a debate of רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon and the רבנן Rabanan if whitening is a שינוי, shinuy, but
even if whitening is a שינוי, shinuy, dyeing it would not be
a שינוי. shinuy. Okay. What?
Dye bleach will remove the color. Right.
Yes. Charlie what you want to say?
Yeah, some dyes actually are really permanent and... Including the most important
one they had back in those times. קלא אילן? Kalla Ilan?
We're going to get to קלא אילן. Kalla Ilan. That the גמרא
Gemara knows is permanent. We're going to get to that. Okay, anyway,
so yes, ironically it's possible that dyeing something is less of a
שינוי shinui than whitening. Why?
More than? Still, wouldn't it be?
No, if it's חוזר לברייתו chozer l'vriyaso is the point here. Yes,
it does look different, but so what? So is turning something into
a garment. But the fact that you can completely undo my Afghan
and turn it into yarn, that's the חידוש chiddush of the גמרא.
Gemara. That even if something's changed substantially and even if undoing it
would require a lot of effort, it still might be considered a
שינוי החוזר לברייתו. shinui hachozer l'vriyaso. It doesn't mean necessarily שינוי
החוזר לברייתו shinui hachozer l'vriyaso too, and that's still a שינוי shinui
depending on.
Not all שינוי השםs shinui hashem are חוזר לברייתו. chozer l'vriyaso. If
I מקדיש makdish something, it's not like you could go to a
חכם chacham and get a היתר, heter, so that's an interesting question.
So you're right, part of the חידוש chiddush here is, and maybe
the answer would be אי נמי, ee nami, part of the חידוש
chiddush of חוזר לברייתו chozer l'vriyaso is not that it can be
trivially reverted. It's that even if it has a significant change and
would require significant effort to revert it, that's part of the חידוש
chiddush of this גמרא Gemara that maybe it's still considered חוזר לברייתו.
chozer l'vriyaso.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, alright, so וכי תימא רב יוחנן
וכי תני התם לא הספיק ליתנה לו עד שצבעו פטור. vechi teima
Rav Yochanan vechi tani hasam lo hispik lisnah lo ad shetzva'o patur.
But how about the fact there that they were only debating the
whitening, but it sounded like everybody agreed that if you dyed it,
it would be a שינוי shinui and you'd be exempt? ואוקימנא כדברי
הכל. v'okimna kidivrei hakol.
That would be בקלא אילן. bekalla ilan. That, as Charlie said, that's
a special dye of קלא אילן kalla ilan which is like a
תכלת-colored techeiles color דלא עבר, delo avar, that that is something that
cannot be, that cannot be taken off. Okay, so therefore, yes, there
are things, it's possible that whitening is a more permanent שינוי shinui
than most types of dyeing. But it is important that the חידוש
chiddush of this גמרא Gemara is again that חוזר לברייתו, chozer l'vriyaso,
the fact it could be reversed, could mean with a lot of
effort and after significant change, that it now is something different. Nevertheless,
the fact that it's possible hypothetically to revert it might be enough
to make it in a weaker category. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. אמר אביי רבי שמעון בן יהודה ובית שמאי ורבי
אליעזר בן יהודה ורבי שמעון בן אלעזר ורבי ישמעאל כולהו סבירא להו.
Amar Abaye Rabbi Shimon ben Yehuda uVeis Shammai v'Rabbi Eliezer ben Yehuda
v'Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar v'Rabbi Yishmael kulehu sevira lehu. So אביי Abaye
is a common thing אביי Abaye does, is if he groups together
different תנאים Tannaim in different places that all reflect a similar type
of an approach. Okay, so he says all of these different תנאים,
Tannaim, כולהו סבירא להו, kulehu sevira lehu, they all have the opinion
that שינוי במקומו עומד. shinui bimkomo omed. That this is the opposite
of שינוי קונה. shinui koneh. שינוי shinui takes possession. It's שינוי במקומו
עומד, shinui bimkomo omed, stands in its place. Now, there's a difference
why he doesn't say שינוי אינו קונה, shinui eino koneh, because שינוי
אינו קונה shinui eino koneh would only be relevant to a discussion
of גניבה וגזילה. gneiva v'gezeila. Does the גנב ganav or גזלן gazlan
take possession? אביי, Abaye, because he's cutting across categories, is going to
show you cases that have nothing to do with taking possession of
it. Okay, but the question is not after it's changed do I
take possession of it? The question is after it's changed, do I
consider it to be the same object or a different object? Okay,
this is like, you know, the perseverance of identity. So שינוי במקומו
עומד shinui bimkomo omed means that even when something undergoes changes, it
still is the same object. Now the question is how radical are
those changes? You know, it's like the gelatin question. Well, no, but
the gelatin question, you know, let's say you completely pulverize something, you
know, and you reduced it like in a laboratory and you completely,
like at what point, you know, at a certain point something does,
okay. But, you know, but when you have these certain types of
changes we're talking about, okay, the position is basically even as things
change, I fundamentally see them as the same thing. Okay, that's all
these תנאים Tannaim have that opinion. So let's take a look. רבי
שמעון בן יהודה הא דאמרן. Rabbi Shimon ben Yehuda ha d'amran. רבי
שמעון בן יהודה Rabbi Shimon ben Yehuda what we just said, that
that was the case of according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that
he was saying that even if you dye it, it is the
same thing. Now, תוספות Tosafos says, you know, again, that's really a
question not of whether he, it's really a question of degree, because
the same רבי שמעון בן יהודה Rabbi Shimon ben Yehuda in the
ברייתא braisa spoke about weaving it and, you know, and spinning it
and all those other types of things where he would say you're
קונה, koneh, where he would say it's a different thing. So
and this is pointed out by a lot of ראשונים Rishonim that
when אביי Abaye says like כולהו סבירא להו, kulehu sevira lehu, he
doesn't mean they're the exact same position. So even if this position
technically believes that שינוי, shinui, you know, is קונה, koneh, שינוי shinui
can be different, he just has a very high threshold for what's
considered to be a שינוי. shinui. Okay, but he's putting it in
the same group. So all of these people either in principle hold
nothing ever changes after a שינוי shinui or what they need to
define something as a שינוי shinui is a very high threshold. So
רבי שמעון בן יהודה Rabbi Shimon ben Yehuda we just discussed about
dyeing the wool. בית שמאי מאי? Beis Shammai mai? What's בית שמאי?
Beis Shammai? And this is something that you might remember from when
we did מרובה. Meruba. דתניא, d'tanya, we taught in a ברייתא. braisa.
נתן לה חטים באתננה. natan lah chitim b'esnanah. Somebody gives a prostitute
wheat as her payment. That's what the אתנן esnan is. And the
תורה Torah says you cannot bring the payment of a prostitute as
a קרבן. korban. Okay, so
now you want to grind it and make it into flour and
make it into a מנחה. mincha. Can you bring that as a
קרבן? korban? ועשאן סולת, va'asaan soles, she turned it into flour. זיתים
zeitim or you gave her olives. ועשאה שמן, Va'asa'ah shemen, she turned
it into oil. Another ענבים, Anavim, grapes, and she turned it into
wine. תני חדא אסור, Tani chada assur, it's still forbidden to be
offered on the מזבח. Mizbeach. ותני אידך, V'tani idach, the other ברייתא
Braisa said מותר, Mutar, it's
permitted. ואמר רב יוסף, V'amar Rav Yosef, תני גויון Tani Goyon from
דמיספרק D'mi-Asparak teaches the following, that it's a debate of בית הלל
ובית שמאי. Beis Hillel v'Beis Shammai.
This is just the מזבח, Mizbeach, but you can only dedicate it
as a... I know, right.
But exactly, it's all מזבח. Mizbeach. בית שמאי אוסרין ובית הלל מתירין.
Beis Shammai osrin u'Beis Hillel matirin. So it's a debate of בית
הלל ובית שמאי. Beis Hillel v'Beis Shammai. מאי טעמא דבית שמאי? Mai
ta'ama d'Beis Shammai? What's the reason of בית שמאי Beis Shammai says
that even after she's changed it, she can't offer it as a
קרבן? Korban? It's not the same thing. No, because אמר קרא, amar
kra, גם שניהם. gam shneihem. It says לא תביא אתנן זונה ומחיר
כלב בית ה' אלוקיך לכל נדר כי תועבת ה' אלוקיך גם שניהם.
Lo savi esnan zona u'mechir kelev beis Hashem Elokecha l'chol neder ki
to'avas Hashem Elokecha gam shneihem. They are both an abomination to God.
So the גם, gam, both, why doesn't it just say שניהם? shneihem?
So that's לרבות שינויהם l'rabos shinuyehem and it's a little play on
the words: שניהם שינויהם. shneihem shinuyehem. So therefore even after they've changed,
it still is the same thing. Now of course you could say
if you needed a פסוק, pasuk, maybe it's a special הלכה halacha
that applies here. Maybe it's not a general position. Okay, but nevertheless,
at least here he holds that even after it's changed, it's still
the same thing. ובית הלל אמר קרא, U'Beis Hillel amar kra, הם,
hem, גם שניהם, gam shneihem, they, they. So they means only them,
ולא שינויהם, v'lo shinuyehem, okay, and not the way in which if
they've changed into something else then not a problem, you can bring
them as a קרבן. Korban. ובית שמאי האי כתיב הם? U'Beis Shammai
hai ksiv hem? What does he do with the הם hem part
of the word שניהם? shneihem? ההוא מיבעי ליה הם ולא ולדותיהם. Hahu
mibaei leh hem v'lo voldoseihem. No, they but not their offspring. If
you give her a sheep and it gives birth to a baby
lamb, that can be brought. That's a that is something different. ובית
הלל תרתי שמעת מינה. U'Beis Hillel tarti shamas mina. No, הם hem
you learn both things, הם בלא שינויהם, hem b'lo shinuyehem, not a
different form that it takes, הם בלא ולדותיהם, hem b'lo voldoseihem, and
not a descendant of them, okay, that it only applies to the
same thing itself. ובית הלל נמי האי כתיב גם? U'Beis Hillel nami
hai ksiv gam? Okay fine, so בית הלל Beis Hillel is very
exacting, only the thing itself is forbidden, nothing else. So what's the
purpose of the word גם? gam? גם gam is even, though in
addition it seems to be broadening the category. No, that's fine, גם
לבית הלל קשיא, gam l'Beis Hillel kashya, that word is difficult for
בית הלל. Beis Hillel. Okay, so of course there's always נחום איש
גם זו, Nachum Ish Gam Zu, okay,
who taught us? He was הלל'ס Hillel's teacher. Who was נחום איש
גם זו'ס Nachum Ish Gam Zu's teacher?
Wasn't he? Charlie's going to find out. That would be funny. Okay,
anyway so the גמרא Gemara says like this. רבי אליעזר בן יעקב
מאי היא? Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov mai hi? What's the רבי אליעזר
בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov that says that even after a
שינוי shinuy something is basically the same? דתניא, D'tanya, we saw it
in the ברייתא, braisa, רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר, Rabbi Eliezer ben
Yaakov omer, הרי שגזל סאה של חיטין, harei she-gazal se'ah shel chitin,
somebody stole a you know whatever a unit of some type of
a measure of wheat. טחנה לשה ואפאה, tchana lasha v'afaa, ground it,
kneaded it and baked it. והפריש ממנה חלה, v'hifrish mimena challah, separated
the חלה, challah, so first of all why didn't you take the
חלה challah before you baked? כיצד מברך? Keitzad mevarech? How can this
person make the ברכה? bracha? Now is he talking about the ברכה
bracha on הפרשת חלה hafrashas challah or the ברכה bracha of המוציא?
Hamotzi? But either way, אין זה מברך אלא מנאץ. ein zeh mevarech
ela m'naetz. In such a case this would not be a ברכה
bracha to God, this would be a blaspheming, okay? Here you are,
you're trying to praise God based on some act of ultimately of
some of theft of yours. So it works better by the way
if it is חלה challah rather than if it's ברכת הנהנין. birchas
ha-nehenin. And then I guess you could say ברכת הנהנין birchas ha-nehenin
because ברכת הנהנין birchas ha-nehenin is understood like by recognizing that this
is all God's we're allowed to derive benefit from it, and here
you
know you're not besides God said not to steal but that also
that it's like the whole idea of a ברכת הנהנין birchas ha-nehenin
is this allows me to derive benefit, you know, I am now
it's now acceptable for me to be נהנה neheneh because now it
is mine, but ultimately it's דווקא davka not yours, you don't have
any right to it. But it works better if it's the חלה
ברכה challah bracha because you know the חלה challah is this is
my thing and I'm now giving of my as a gift to
God, right? A first separating of the dough to God and here
it's like how do you think that this is giving something off
something to God, you know, this is ultimately something that you stole?
That's an act the גמרא'ס Gemara's going to compare it, it's like
a classic, you know, מצוה הבאה בעבירה mitzvah ha-ba'ah b'aveirah in the
sense of a גזל gezel of a קרבן. Korban. You steal a
קרבן, Korban, you think you're going to offer it up? You steal
flour, you know, dough and you think you're going to give it
as a gift to God through the חלה? challah? Although it is
interesting that it emphasizes the ברכה, bracha, you know, the words are
a curse, not necessarily just the act. Yeah, Rabbi Dov.
That's precisely the interplay between the previous example because the previous example
it's interesting it doesn't say מנאץ m'naetz with the prostitute. There it's
an issue of a קרבן Korban and it's definitely an issue of
הנאה, hana'ah, right? So in other words there's one leads into the
other. It's sort of playing. Right, right.
I mean you definitely have the wheat that's been transported transformed in
some type of a gift to God, yes.
Charlie. נחום איש גם זו Nachum Ish Gam Zu was רבי עקיבא'ס.
Rabbi Akiva's.
רבי עקיבא'ס Rabbi Akiva's teacher, that's right. Okay, so it didn't work.
Okay, anyway, so how come we're not linking any of this?
We are going to. All the possible different differences we are going
to.
You mean above we didn't mention it, you know, about אתנן עשאה,
esnan asaa, you know, חיטין עשאה סולת. chitin asaa solet.
What are you talking about? What didn't we mention? The מניין Minayin
idea? Well, first of all, this is his דרשה. Drasha. He happened
to be talking about this. Maybe he would say the same about
the same. But this, but that's different. There was something she received
and it's not a question about theft and not belonging, right? I
understand it's a problem about a שינוי, Shinuy, you know, I understand
but it's a different point. I understand but it's different. Also he's
talking about a ברכה Bracha and the words of a ברכה Bracha
being a curse. Anyway he has a דרשה Drasha based on a
פסוק. Pasuk. Okay? So ועל זה נאמר Ve'al Zeh Ne'emar in regarding
this it said בוצע ברך ניאץ ה׳. Botzea Berech Ni'etz Hashem. So
one who breaks bread and blesses—בוצע Botzea could mean בצע Betza like
an ill-gotten gain, okay, who's blessing, it's a play on words, but
also you're בוצע Botzea on the לחם. Lechem. So it's the bread
that you stole that's ill-gotten, okay, and your blessing, that person's blessing
is a cursing of God. So that makes it sound like it's
המוציא, Hamotzi, right. Okay. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר מאי? Rabbi Shimon Ben
Elazar Mai? What's רבי שמעון בן אלעזר? Rabbi Shimon Ben Elazar? דתניא
Detanya anyway the point is, why is it a problem? It's something
different. Look at all the שינוי Shinuy he did. No, doesn't matter,
still the same object. Of course his reasons to say that's a
little bit of a different case, but anyway the גמרא Gemara will
get to that. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר מאי? Rabbi Shimon Ben Elazar
Mai? דתניא, Detanya, כלל זה אמר רבי שמעון בן אלעזר, Klal Zeh
Amar Rabbi Shimon Ben Elazar, כל שבח Kol Shevach now we're getting
back to our גניבה Gneivah and גזילה Gzeilah case. כל שבח שהשביח
גזלן ידו על העליונה. Kol Shevach She'hishbiach Gazlan Yado Al Ha'elyonah. Any
improvement that the גזלן Gazlan makes in the object he stole, he
has the upper hand. He gets to decide. רצה נוטל שבחו, Ratza
Notel Shivcho,
if he wants he can get paid for he can take his
improvement, okay, so if he basically I don't know, you know,
fattened the cow, that'd be a good example. He fattened the cow,
he gets to take back maybe get paid for the amount that
he improved it, okay, which is a fascinating idea. Why? If it's
not a שינוי Shinuy and the owner still owns it or whatever.
Okay, רצה נוטל שבחו רצה אומר לו הרי שלך לפניך. Ratza Notel
Shivcho Ratza Omer Lo Harei Shelcha Lifanecha. If he wants he can
say הרי שלך לפניך, Harei Shelcha Lifanecha, take it. So the גמרא
Gemara says מאי קאמר? Mai Ka'amar? What are you talking about? Those
are two separate cases. The case he would want to say is
yours, take it back, is when it's not worth more. The case
he wants take what it's worth more is when it is worth
more. What does that sentence mean? So the גמרא Gemara says, מאי
קאמר, Mai Ka'amar, אמר רב ששת הכי קאמר. Amar Rav Sheshet Hachi
Ka'amar. This is what he means. השביח, Hishbiach, it means either or,
doesn't mean the same case. השביח, Hishbiach, if he improved it, נוטל
שבחו, Notel Shivcho, he can take the improvement. אם הכחיש, Im Hikchish,
if it got worse, אומר לו הרי שלך לפניך. Omer Lo Harei
Shelcha Lifanecha. דשינוי במקומו עומד, De'shinuy Bimkomo Omed, that so we're not
going to focus on the why did he get to take back
the שבח Shevach although we'll have to ask that in a second,
we're first going to focus on the second part. The fact that
he
can always say הרי שלך לפניך Harei Shelcha Lifanecha seems to say
that the principle is שינוי במקומו עומד. Shinuy Bimkomo Omed. I mean
why doesn't he distinguish what type of cases can you say הרי
שלך לפניך? Harei Shelcha Lifanecha? It sounds like you can blanket say
it, it's always the same object. Yes.
So there's a great entrepreneurial incentive to steal, right? You can steal
an item
and then if
it goes up in price you get to keep the difference.
I know. There's like no disincentive according to הלכה. Halacha. I mean
if you're not afraid about how God will punish you or your
standing in society, there's no there is no real legal incentive not
to steal. And even if you're caught by גזילה Gzeilah you just
have to give it back.
Right? כפל? Kefel?
No, that's only if you're נשבע, Nishba, right? If you take an
oath. If you basically are a גנב, Ganav, if you're not a
גנב Ganav if you're just a גזלן, Gazlan, okay, and you're upfront
about it or whatever, you know the worst that can happen to
you is you have to pay it back. I mean you know
how God will punish you is a different story, but yeah that's
a big problem. Anyway so the גמרא Gemara says like this. דשינוי
במקומו עומד. De'shinuy Bimkomo Omed.
The fact that he says you can always say הרי שלך לפניך
Harei Shelcha Lifanecha shows like we said that it's always considered the
same object. So אי הכי Ei Hachi says the גמרא Gemara אפילו
השביח נמי, Afilu Hishbiach Nami, even if it improved it's the same
object, you should have to give it back. So אמר רבי מפני
תקנת השבים. Amar Rabbi Mipnei Takanas Hashavin. No, no, no, that's to
make it easier for people to do תשובה Teshuvah so a guy
says look I mean I've been spending this last year fattening this
cow, costed me all this money, now I'm going to have to
give it back to the owner? It's easier not to give it
back to the owner. So to incentivize people to return the object
and as you pointed out like there's always what's the incentive to
return anyway? You know, but I guess if there's no fine, you
know at least it won't be maybe just your own conscience is
your incentive. Anyway we have to make it easier and therefore you
get to actually be paid back for the amount that you improved
it, okay, which is really shocking. We're going to continue today in
a bit in a while to talk about תקנת השבים. Takanas Hashavin.
Okay so basically the object is always the same,
the owner always has a right to take it back, but if
you improved it to make it not that that shouldn't be an
obstacle for you to return it, we're going to be able to
be compensated for the amount that you improved it.
Does that actually mean the בית דין Beis Din will go and
say all right you have to pay him or is it only
if the
גזלן Gazlan asks?
Good question. I don't know. It's a good question. What are the
parameters? We're going to see in a minute when we get to
תקנת השבים Takanas Hashavin that it's going to seem like the בית
דין Beis Din was very proactive in תקנת השבים. Takanas Hashavin. So
we'll see about that.
רבי ישמעאל מאי? Rabbi Yishmael Mai? What's רבי ישמעאל? Rabbi Yishmael? דתניא
Detanya we talked in a ברייתא. Braisa. מצוות פאה Mitzvas Pe'ah the
idea of leaving the corner of the field, להפריש מן הקמה Lehafrish
Min Hakama to set it aside from the standing grain. לא הפריש
מן הקמה Lo Hafrish Min Hakama if you didn't set it aside
from the standing grain, מפריש מן העומרים Mafrish Min Ha'omarim even after
you've made it into sheaves. לא הפריש מן העומרים Lo Hafrish Min
Ha'omarim if you've... If you didn't separate it when the wheat had
been turned into sheaves, you didn't leave, then it's not a corner
of the field, but it's you leave over some sheaves. If you
didn't do that, לא הפריש מן
העומרים, lo hifrish min ha'omarim, מפריש מן הכרי, mafrish min hakari, after
you've threshed the grain and you've made it now into
this mound of grain, you've removed it from the stalks, then you
can also leave a little bit over as now makeup פאה. peah.
Obviously it's certainly not a corner of the field at this stage.
עד שלא מרחו, ad shelo mircho, until you have not done the
מירוח. meiruach. The מירוח meiruach is the smoothing of the כרי kari
and the מירוח meiruach means that you become obligated in תרומות trumos
and מעשרות. maasros. And the importance here is the following, that all
the gifts to the poor are exempt from תרומות trumos and מעשרות.
maasros. So, if you give it any stage before מירוח, meiruach, the
poor can take it and remain exempt from תרומות trumos and מעשרות,
maasros, like he would have been when he took it when it
was standing wheat. After you did the מירוח, meiruach, the smoothing, that
creates the obligation of the grain now must have תרומות trumos and
מעשרות maasros taken from it. So even if you give it to
the poor, since it's reached this level of processing, it's obligated in
תרומות trumos and מעשרות. maasros. That's not fair now to the poor.
Normally their gift wouldn't have had that, they wouldn't have had to
do that and now they have to do it. So here's what's
going to happen.
מרחו, mircho, if you already did the smoothing, then מעשר ונותן לו,
maaser v'nosein lo, first you do the תרומות trumos and מעשרות maasros
and then you give it to him. So what he's getting is
free from תרומות trumos and מעשרות. maasros. Now, רבי ישמעאל
אמרו, Rabbi Yishmael omru, in the משום רבי ישמעאל אמרו, mishum Rabbi
Yishmael omru, in the name of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael they said
אף מפריש מן העיסה ונותן לו, af mafrish min ha'isa v'nosein lo,
even after it's turned into dough, you give the poor person פאה.
peah. So until that point you could say it's not a real
שינוי. shinui. It's still, I mean, the עיקר ikar thing that the
wheat was standing and now it's cut, but the real thing that
the poor is getting is he's getting the grain. And the grain
until that point fundamentally, like it's been taken out of its container
as it were, but it hasn't really transformed. But רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael says even if it's been made into flour and into dough,
you still have to give it, so you see it's still considered
to be the same thing for
רבי ישמעאל.
Rabbi Yishmael. So, what? If you baked it?
I don't know. אמר ליה רב פפא לאביי, amar lei Rav Pappa
l'Abaye, so רב פפא Rav Pappa said to אביי, Abaye, איכא כל
הני תנאי לאשמועינן כבית שמאי, ika kol hani tana'ei l'ashmueinan k'Beis Shammai,
I don't understand, you think these are all saying the basic same
position? So all of a sudden all these תנאים tana'im hold like
בית שמאי? Beis Shammai? So which basically means he's skeptical that they
really would all agree with one another. Maybe every one is unique
to their own case. Really everybody holds like בית שמאי Beis Shammai
here? אמר ליה הכי קאמר, amar lei hachi ka'amar, this is what
I'm saying, or this is what they would say, לא נחלקו גבי
בית שמאי ובית הלל בהא, lo nechelu gabei Beis Shammai u'Beis Hillel
b'ha, no, they'd claim it wasn't a debate of בית הלל Beis
Hillel and בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. They'd claim that everybody held like
that, that this is true, that even after something changes it's still
the same identity. So now the גמרא gemara is going to poke
holes in this. אמר רבא, amar Rava, רבא Rava said ממי, mimai,
what makes you think they're all holding the same thing? דילמא עד
כאן לא קאמר רבי שמעון בן יהודה התם, dilma ad kan lo
ka'amar Rabbi Shimon ben Yehuda hasam, why does רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
say dyeing is not a שינוי? shinui? אלא בצבע, ela betzeva, that's
only the specific case of dyeing. It's not like he doesn't hold
to the principle. It's just it doesn't apply in that case. דהוי
יכול להעבירו על ידי צבע, de'havi yakhol l'ha'aviro al yedei tzeva, because
it could be, the dye could be taken out by a type
of a dye
remover. So it's a reversible שינוי. shinui. ועד כאן לא קאמרי בית
שמאי התם, v'ad kan lo ka'amri Beis Shammai hasam, בית שמאי Beis
Shammai only said that there by the gift to the אתנן, esnan,
אלא גבוה, ela gavo'ah, that's a special הלכה halacha about something that
was going to be offered as a קרבן, korban, משום דמאיס, mishum
d'mi'is, because then it's become disgusting that this was used in this
way. So therefore the, we'll see the continuity of identity
in different ways than we would see it in other הלכות, halachos,
because we have higher standards when it's about bringing something as a
קרבן. korban. ועד כאן לא קאמר רבי אליעזר בן יעקב התם, v'ad
kan lo ka'amar Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov hasam, and when רבי אליעזר
בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov says that that's a, that's a,
not a ברכה, bracha, but like a blaspheming, אלא בברכה, ela b'vracha,
because of a ברכה. bracha. Now you could have said the same
idea, it's like a קרבן, korban, something that's a ברכה, bracha, it's
a religious act that you're doing with it and so on, it
has a higher standard. But he now introduces a new way, not
just saying the ברכה bracha makes it like a קרבן korban or
make חלה challah like a קרבן. korban. He says the following thing,
משום דהוי ליה מצוה הבאה בעבירה. mishum d'havei lei mitzvah haba'ah b'aveira.
Ah, which is because and that's so that's not a ברכה bracha
anymore. That and that seems to be evoking the חלה challah aspect
of it, not the ברכה bracha aspect of it. But the point
being that when you're dealing with things like ברכות brachos and מצוות
mitzvos and so on, if they come as a result of a
sin, it maybe has nothing to, it's a different standard, as we
could sort of say it's like the קרבן korban standard, higher standards.
You could also say that maybe it's not about the object. The
phrase מצוה הבאה בעבירה, mitzvah haba'ah b'aveira, could sound like the מצוה
mitzvah was enabled through a sin. So the מצוה mitzvah was enabled
through a sin, we don't have to say that the bread is
the same is the same object that you stole. That's the whole
question of מצוה הבאה בעבירה. mitzvah haba'ah b'aveira. Is it invalidating the
object to be used, a stolen לולב lulav is a פסול לולב,
pasul lulav, a stolen קרבן korban is a פסול קרבן, pasul korban,
like the אתנן, esnan, something given as a gift to a prostitute
is stigmatized,
is tainted and can't be used, or is מצוה הבאה בעבירה mitzvah
haba'ah b'aveira about the process? A מצוה mitzvah that was enabled through
a sin is not a legitimate מצווה. mitzvah. Okay, so that's another
way of saying. So who cares if it's a שינוי? shinui? It's
still about it was enabled through a sin.
No, but the חפצא cheftza retains its—
No, that's what I was pushing back. You don't have to say
the object retains its identity. It could be a different object but
the מצווה mitzvah was still enabled through a sin. Okay, ועד כאן
לאוקמי רבי שמעון בן אלעזר התם, ve'ad kan l'okmi Rabbi Shimon ben
Elazar hasam, and how about רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben
Elazar when he says if it got weak you can return it,
who says he's talking about everything? He talked about if it got
thinner, אלא בכחושי, ela bechashei, that's getting thinner, דהדר, dehadar, that can
revert also. By the way, not only would you have to say
it could revert itself, אכחושי achashei you could just say doesn't change
its identity, right? Remember תוספות Tosafos said, even שינוי מעשה, shinui maaseh,
even if you like plane wood and smooth out stones, if it
still is called the same thing, then it's still that's not a
שינוי. shinui. A שינוי shinui has to start by us giving it
a different label. So a thinner cow doesn't exactly have a different
label than a fatter cow. Okay, so anyway, בשום דהדר, bishum dehadar,
so the גמרא Gemara says because it could be reverted. ועד כאן
למימר ליה לרבי ישמעאל התם, ve'ad kan lemar lei Rabbi Yishmael hasam,
and why did רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael say you gave פאה peah
even after it's changed? אלא ענין פאה, ela inyan peah, that's a
special פאה peah הלכה, halacha, משום דכתיב, mishum dechaseiv, the verse says
תעזוב, ta'azov, it says לעני ולגר תעזוב אותם. le'ani uleger ta'azov osam.
And multiple times does the פסוק pasuk say by these agricultural gifts
to the poor, תעזוב, ta'azov, תעזוב, ta'azov, תעזוב. ta'azov.
So it says it an extra time, יתירא, yeseira, to tell you
that even after your obligation should have ceased because it's now changed,
you still have to give it.
Okay, וכי תימא ליגמר מיניה, vechi teima ligmor minei, okay, why don't
we use that as a principle to learn from, right? I mean,
the other things you explained why they were very different, like things
to God, things as a מצווה, mitzvah, but this is like more
like a question of ownership, right? It's something the poor owns. So
if you still seize you still have to give them what they
own even after you've changed it, so maybe that should be a
general principle even for גזילה, gezeilah, that even after something has changed,
it still belongs to the owner? That there it is a more
comparable the idea of the poor and the question of ownership. וכי
תימא ליגמר מיניה, vechi teima ligmor minei, why don't we learn from
that? No, מתנות עניים שאני, matnos aniyim shani, maybe still it's a
special thing for gifts to the poor and it is not a
general הלכה. halacha. כדיבעי רבי יונתן, kedi'baei Rabbi Yonasan, like רבי יונתן
Rabbi Yonasan asked, דבעי רבי יונתן, dibaei Rabbi Yonasan, one minute, רבי
יונתן Rabbi Yonasan asked,
מאי טעמא דרבי ישמעאל? mai ta'ama deRabbi Yishmael? What's the reason of
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael that he says you have to give it
even after you turned it into flour into
dough? משום דקסבר שינוי אינו קונה? mishum dekasavar shinui eino koneh? Does
he hold that שינוי shinui does not קונה? koneh? Notice by the
way the language switched from שינוי בעלמא אמר shinui be'almo amar to
שינוי אינו קונה, shinui eino koneh, because when you're dealing with gifts
to the poor you are dealing with more of a question of
ownership. Okay, so is it because he feels that שינוי shinui does
not change ownership and therefore it's still the poor still have rights
to it?
או דלמא, o dilma, or does he hold, בעלמא קסבר שינוי קונה?
be'almo kasavar shinui koneh? Really שינוי shinui does work. והכא משום דכתיב
תעזוב יתירא, vehacha mishum dechaseiv ta'azov yeseira, it's a special exception by
the gifts to the poor because it says an extra time you
should leave it.
ואם תמצא לומר טעמא דרבי ישמעאל משום דקסבר שינוי אינו קונה, ve'im
timtzei lomar ta'ama deRabbi Yishmael mishum dekasavar shinui eino koneh, now one
minute, if you think that רבי ישמעאל's's Rabbi Yishmael reason is that
שינוי shinui is as a rule is not קונה, koneh, תעזוב יתירא
דכתב רחמנא למה לי? ta'azov yeseira dechazav rachmana lamli? So if he
held it as a universal principle, why would he need the extra
תעזוב? ta'azov? Of course you could say he learns it as an
universal principle from the fact that the תורה Torah says תעזוב, ta'azov,
but nevertheless the גמרא Gemara says, ותו לרבנן תעזוב יתירא דכתב רחמנא
למה לי? v'tu leRabbanan ta'azov yeseira dechazav rachmana lamli? For the רבנן
Rabbanan who hold that you're not obligated to give it after you've
turned it into dough, what do they do with the fact that
the תורה Torah repeats the word תעזוב? ta'azov?
It is קונה koneh after the שינוי. shinui.
Why order to
תעזוב ta'azov repeat it again?
Not תוספות Tosafos quoted, many times in the תורה Torah it says
תעזוב ta'azov by the same מתנות עניים. matnos aniyim. Different פסוקים, pesukim,
not one פסוק. pasuk. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, מיבעי ליה
לכדתניא, miba'ei lei lachada tanya, like we taught in a ברייתא, Baraisa,
המפקיר כרמו, hamafkir karmo, if you basically announced, oh my vineyard is
הפקר, hefker, anybody can come and take it. Of course you said
that at 1 AM in the morning. Okay, so so that nobody
was able to act on it. והשכים בבוקר ובצרו, vehishkim baboker ubetzaro,
and then you woke up in the morning and you harvested it.
Okay, so it was הפקר hefker for a few hours. חייב בפרט
ובעוללות ובשכחה ופאה, chayav beperet ve'ololos uveshichecha peah, that doesn't exempt you,
the fact that it was הפקר hefker for a brief period of
time does not exempt you from any of the gifts to the
poor. Okay, פרט peret and עוללות ololos are certain types of unformed
grapes that are left to the poor and things that you forget
and the corner. ופטור מן המעשר, upatur min hamaser, and you're exempt
from מעשר. maser. There's a הלכה halacha מעשר maser is also if
something is הפקר hefker it's exempt from מעשר. maser. So if it
even if it was only הפקר hefker for a few hours that
exempts it from מעשר, maser, but not the gifts to the poor.
Which why? You see that the poor's rights to it are more
that are greater more persistent than other things. That's the extra תעזוב.
ta'azov. Even though it was הפקר hefker for a few hours and
in other areas that might exempt you, it doesn't exempt you from
gifts to the poor.
הפקר hefker is a שינוי. shinui.
No, הפקר hefker is a different הלכה. halacha. הפקר hefker is the
status that it's it goes to the poor, that הפקר hefker gets
you out of obligations of תרומות ומעשרות, terumos u'maaseros, but it doesn't
get you out of obligations of מתנות עניים matnos aniyim because of
the extra תעזוב. ta'azov. Okay, so ופטור מן המעשר. u'patur min ha-maiser.
So therefore, as it is an ex- you have to give the
פאה, pe'ah, the מתנות לעניים matanos l'aniyim to the poor even in
cases where you wouldn't have to give it in other parallel circumstances
by other things. So that's certainly true in the case of if
it were הפקר hefker for a few hours. By מעשר maiser you
get off your obligation, but not by your gifts to the poor.
What about after it changed? So there, the רבי ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael
says there also I say, even after it changed, even if in
other areas you would be קונה, koneh, it would be a different
thing, by the gifts to the poor you still have to give
it. And the רבנן Rabanan say no, if it's physically changed, you
don't have to give it even as a gift to the poor.
Yes.
There's another difference between these. So these מצוות mitzvos take effect much
earlier than say מעשר עני. maiser ani. And nobody ever mentioned מעשר
עני. maiser ani. It might be possible that מעשר עני maiser ani
is different.
Oh, you mean when we say the תעזוב יתירה, ta'azov yeseira, yeah,
no, that's a good point, but these like when I say gifts
to the poor I'm speaking a little generic, you know, פאה, pe'ah,
לקט, leket, שכחה, shich'cha, etc. You're right. It's not the מעשר. maiser.
The מעשר עני maiser ani which is only given two out of
every seven years, that would be treated as standard מעשר, maiser, right?
These are the specific things that are left to the poor, that's
why the word תעזוב. ta'azov. It doesn't say תעזוב ta'azov by מעשר
עני. maiser ani. תעזוב ta'azov means you leave it in the field,
right? So you're exactly right. It's those types of things. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this. So we have all these
positions that you could sort of say oh looks like they're all
saying that שינוי shinuy doesn't make a difference, but when you get
down to it, they might be speaking very locally about their specific
cases. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר רב
יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel, הלכה כרבי שמעון בן
אלעזר. halacha k'Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar. We rule like רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר. Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar. Now we're going way back to the
whole case about the dying of the wool. Okay, so רבי שמעון
בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar says that even after you dye
the wool it's not a שינוי. shinuy. Okay, now again does that
mean in principle he doesn't hold of שינוי shinuy or he just
has a high threshold of what defines שינוי? shinuy? The גמרא Gemara
now thinks for a moment that it means in principle he doesn't
hold of שינוי. shinuy. ומי אמר שמואל הכי? u'mi amar Shmuel hachi?
Did שמואל Shmuel really say that a שינוי shinuy isn't קונה? koneh?
והאמר שמואל ve'ha'amar Shmuel אין שמין לא לגנב ולא לגזלן אלא לנזיקין.
ein shamin lo l'ganav v'lo l'gazlan ela l'nezikin. Anybody remember that line
of שמואל? Shmuel? Which is the animal dies and you know my
animal- if the animal fell in the well, do I pay- do
I take the whole- the dead carcass it was my well and
pay you for the whole animal, or is it your carcass and
I pay the difference? So that's the question of שמין. shamin. You
assess the damages. So שמואל Shmuel says you only assess the damages
in a case of damaging of you know my well, my fire,
I physically broke something, then it's your object and I pay you
for the difference. Okay, but if it is a case of a
גנב ganav and a גזלן, gazlan, okay, when I take- steal the
object, I become liable in the entire amount. So if therefore we
don't have to ask the question about you know about what's the
sort of you know cost of the difference etc. because it's- wait
a minute am I saying this right?
Hold on. Yes I am saying it right. One minute.
Right right. If it dies, right, if it just gets weaker. If
the animal dies, if I steal your cow and the animal dies,
then it's- then then it's then it's a שינוי קונה. shinuy koneh.
It becomes my cow and therefore I have to go ahead- so
if I damage your object, there's never שינוי קונה. shinuy koneh. It
was your object and now it's now it's broken and it's dead
and whatever and I pay you the difference. But if I steal
it and it dies, then it's שינוי קונה shinuy koneh and I
pay you for the whole animal, you don't have to assess the
difference, I pay you for the whole animal. Okay, so והאמר שמואל
ve'ha'amar Shmuel אין שמין לא לגנב ולא לגזלן. ein shamin lo l'ganav
v'lo l'gazlan. You don't assess the difference. Only for case of נזיקין
nezikin damages, but for case of גנב וגזלן ganav v'gazlan it's a
שינוי shinuy and you pay for the whole animal. So- so how
does that work if שמואל Shmuel is also פוסק paskening like רבי
שמעון בן יהודה? Rabbi Shimon ben Yehuda? About the case that dying
the wool, a different type of dying, dying the wool you're not-
you're not קונה. koneh. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: בשלמא
לרבא, bishlama l'Rava, it works according to רבא, Rava, דאמר כי קאמר
רבי שמעון בן אלעזר התם בהכחשה. d'amar ki ka'amar Rebbi Shimon ben
Elazar hatam b'hach'chasha. I'm sorry that's not the רבי שמעון בן אלעזר,
Rebbi Shimon ben Elazar, that's not the- this is רבי שמעון- oh
that was רבי שמעון בן יהודה, I mistaken. My mistake, my mistake,
not the dying of the wool. This is even a more similar
case. This is רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rebbi Shimon ben Elazar about
stealing the animal and it getting weaker and he says you could
say הרי שלך לפניך. harei shelcha l'fanecha. So the גמרא Gemara thinks
that's similar to the case of stealing an animal and it's dying.
So why is it that שמואל Shmuel could פוסק pasken that if
you steal the animal it gets thinner you could return it, but
if you steal it and it dies you're קונה? koneh? So according
to רבא Rava it makes sense, there's a big difference between it
getting thinner and between it dying. בשלמא לרבא דאמר כי קאמר רבי
שמעון בן אלעזר התם בהכחשה דהדר. bishlama l'Rava d'amar ki ka'amar Rebbi
Shimon ben Elazar hatam b'hach'chasha d'hadar. He's only saying it about getting
thinner. That's something that could revert. לא קשיא, lo kashya, that's not
difficult. כי קאמר כרבי שמעון בן אלעזר. ki ka'amar k'Rebbi Shimon ben
Elazar. When does שמואל Shmuel say we rule like רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר Rebbi Shimon ben Elazar דשינוי במקומו עומד? d'shinuy bimkomo omed? That
a שינוי shinuy does not-
does not make you own it? בהכחשה דהדר. b'hach'chasha d'hadar. If it
can be reverted. Again I don't know why שמואל Shmuel even say
that there's not a שינוי השם shinuy hashem there. Anyway. וכי קאמר
שמואל התם. ve'chi ka'amar Shmuel hatam. And when does שמואל Shmuel say
there that you actually do own the object and you have to
pay full value, you know, אין שמין לא לגנב ולא לגזלן אלא
לנזיקין? ein shamin lo l'ganav v'lo l'gazlan ela l'nezikin? בהכחשה דלא הדר.
b'hach'chasha d'la hadar. Some type of- of a change like it died
or it broke a leg, that it's not going to get better.
And if it's not going to get better, then you are קונה
koneh it. Okay fine, it's not a
problem. but אביי Abaye said that רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon
ben Elazar rejects the whole position of שינוי קונה, shinuy koneh, that
he said that doesn't matter what happens to the object, you can
always return it, right? That's אביי'ס Abaye's read, that he in principle
holds שינוי shinuy does nothing. So if that's true, how could שמואל
Shmuel פוסקן pasken like רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar
and פוסקן pasken אין שמין? ein shamin? מאי איכא למימר? mai ikka
lemeimar? How do you reconcile the two פסקים psakim of שמואל? Shmuel?
So אביי Abaye מתני הכי. masni hachi. So אביי Abaye teaches it
the following way. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל. amar Rav Yehuda amar
Shmuel. רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said in the name of שמואל, Shmuel,
אמרו. amru.
There are those that say that הלכה כרבי שמעון בן אלעזר, halakha
ke-Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar, that we rule like רבי שמעון בן אלעזר.
Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar. ומיהו לא שויה, u-mi-hu la shavye, but that's
not really שמואל'ס Shmuel's position. Okay. So basically he completely changes the
quote. It's not that שמואל Shmuel פוסקנס paskens like רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר. Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar. רב יהודה Rav Yehuda argues on those
who פוסקן pasken like רבי שמעון בן אלעזר. Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar.
Alright, anyway, clearly it makes much, much more sense to read this
like אביי, Abaye, like רבא, Rava, that people are not arguing the
principle that an object can change its identity. The question is what
degree of change is needed? Maybe in certain categories of הלכה, halakha,
there are special exceptions to the rules, but in principle nobody's coming
with a blanket idea that שינוי shinuy doesn't mean anything. Okay. אמר
רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן. amar Rabbi Hiyya bar Abba
amar Rabbi Yochanan. Said רבי חייא בר אבא Rabbi Hiyya bar Abba
in the name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, דבר תורה, devar Torah,
from the, from a biblical perspective, גזילה המשתנית חוזרת בעיניה. gezeilah ha-mishtanit
chozeret be-einha. So after just complete saying what I just said, right,
that it sounds like everybody in principle agrees to it, now we
have a statement in the name of, or certainly bracketing אביי, Abaye,
now we have a statement in the name of רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan that says no, actually biblically speaking, everybody agrees that even after
change it would go back. Okay.
שנאמר והשיב את הגזילה אשר גזל. shene'emar ve-heshiv et ha-gezeilah asher gazal.
Return the object that you stole מכל מקום, mi-kol makom, regardless. Now
it's very funny, the גמרא Gemara reads אשר גזל asher gazal in
two completely opposite ways. אשר גזל asher gazal means כאשר גזל, ka-asher
gazal, if it is in the state it was when you stole
it, so exactly to tell you that if it's changed you don't
have to return it. And here we're reading it in the exact
opposite way. Return what you stole in whatever, whatever condition it's in
now, return that object. Okay. I don't care what's happened to it,
return that object. Okay. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is saying, now
who knows? Maybe we'd say in other cases שינוי shinuy does matter.
Maybe he's saying that גניבה'ס g'neivah's like we said before about, like
we said about the case of עצו ופסירו. atzo u-p'seiro. I don't
know what גזילה, gezeilah, I don't know what שינוי shinuy is in
other cases in the, in the תורה, Torah, but by גזילה gezeilah
from the תורה'ס Torah's perspective, you gotta return it regardless of the
state that it's in. Now again, is that a קולא kula or
a חומרא? chumra? Right? Does that mean that even if it's dead
I can say הרי שלך לפניך? harei shelcha lefanecha? Or does it
mean even if now it's a much better object I still have
to and diff and I made it into a whole, I stole
your lumber and I built it into a whole house, you now
take title of the house? That it could be a קולא kula
or a חומרא. chumra. But he is saying whatever the הלכה halakha
is in general, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is saying we'll get to
the, the, the הלכה halakha in the משנה, Mishnah, right, which clearly
recognizes שינוי, shinuy, but from the תורה'ס Torah's perspective, by גזילה gezeilah
you always return it.
One thing we haven't mentioned at all, this is יאוש. ye'ush. So,
correct.
יאוש ye'ush is really not a conversation by שינוי. shinuy. יאוש ye'ush
is a conversation about, maybe by שינוי שם, shinuy shem, not שינוי
מעשה. shinuy ma'aseh. Okay, let's not worry about it. Okay. שנאמר והשיב
את הגזילה אשר גזל מכל מקום. shene'emar ve-heshiv et ha-gezeilah asher gazal
mi-kol makom. ואם תאמר משנתנו, ve-im tomar Mishnatenu, what about our משנה?
Mishnah? Our משנה Mishnah says, you know, you stole wood and you
made it into a, into a instrument, you have to return it?
So no, משום תקנת השבים, mishum takanat ha-shavin, it's a תקנת השבים
takanat ha-shavin we said before. So here he says תקנת השבים takanat
ha-shavin is the only reason why you find in rabbinic literature the
idea that שינוי shinuy means the גנב ganav or גזלן gazlan can
keep it. It's all a דרבנן de-rabbanan הלכה halakha to make go
easy on the גנב. ganav. Okay, because and that's cases when your
שינוי shinuy made it better. You stole wood and turned it into
a table and a chair, and a, whatever, now I'm gonna have
to return this gorgeous table I here I just made this gorgeous
table here out of the wood I stole. I'm gonna have to
return, forget it, I'm not returning that. Or would be difficult. Well,
right. No, but forget yeah. So the that
we'll get to that in a minute. So anyway he basically says
that all the הלכות halakhot of שינוי קונה shinuy koneh are to
make it easier for a גזלן gazlan to do תשובה. teshuvah. Or
to not we don't necessarily care about the guys, him and God
and whether his personal sort of תשובה, teshuvah, but we want the
object back. You know, ultimately it's for the benefit of society. תקנת
השבים, takanat ha-shavin, I should make the point,
it is not
you have to sacrifice your interests in order to let this guy
do תשובה. teshuvah. No, no. It's in everybody's benefit to let him
do this because that'll actually get
you compensated. It'll get him to come forward and get you compensated.
Yeah, let's just say like really concretely, so you stole a hundred
dollars worth of lumber. Right. And you made a table now worth
a thousand dollars.
Right. According to the תורה, Torah, you should have to give the
original owner the whole table. Right.
וחכמים, ve-Hakhamim, you get to keep the table and you just pay
him for the lumber.
So you pay him how much?
A hundred dollars. כשעת גזילה. kish'at gezeilah.
Just a hundred dollars and you've got the שבח Shevach of nine
hundred dollars. Exactly. It's a great סברא! Svara! Exactly.
Okay so now okay but anyway this is a really shocking idea.
He says we've just talked about specific cases that the תורה Torah
explicitly says I don't care about a שינוי, shinuy, גזילה gezeilah also
the תורה Torah really says I don't care about a שינוי, shinuy,
return it anyway, but the חכמים Chachamim say we're going to have
to change that, change that, haha. We're going to have to say
that after it's changed, okay, the גזלן gazlan gets to keep it
and he only has to pay back the money. ואם תאמר משום
שינוי משום תקנת השבים. V'im tomar mishum shinuy mishum takanas hashavim. Okay
ומי אמר רבי יוחנן הכי? umi amar Rabi Yochanan hachi? Did Rabbi
Yochanan really say that? והאמר רבי יוחנן הלכה כסתם משנה, V'ha'amar Rabi
Yochanan halacha k'stam Mishna, we rule like a סתם משנה, stam Mishna,
ותנן, u'tnan, and we taught in the משנה: Mishna: לא הספיק ליתנו
לו עד שצבעו, Lo hispik litno lo ad shetzva'o,
you did not have a chance again, this is the case of
the ראשית הגז, reishis hageiz, to give it to the כהן kohein
until you dyed it, פטור, patur, you're exempt. Now why is that
a problem? Because that shows you that that's not a question of
תקנת השבים, takanas hashavim, it's my wool, I dyed my wool, it's
a question of my obligation in ראשית הגז reishis hageiz to the
כהן, kohein, and we're recognizing a שינוי. shinuy. Okay, so how are
we recognizing, so therefore if it says that, the תורה Torah recognizes
a שינוי shinuy by ראשית הגז, reishis hageiz, it gets me out
of my obligation. So why shouldn't it recognize it by גזילה? gezeilah?
Now again you could say maybe גזילה gezeilah is an exception, okay,
but but at least we see that in principle in other places
the תורה Torah recognizes a שינוי. shinuy. How could you say it
doesn't recognize a שינוי shinuy here? So אמר להו ההוא מרבנן ורבי
יעקב שמיה, amar lehu hahu merabanan v'Rabi Yaakov shemei, one of the
rabbis and his name was Rabbi Yaakov said, לדידי מפרשא לי מיניה
דרבי יוחנן, l'didi mefarsha li minei d'Rabi Yochanan, as for me it
was explained to me by Rabbi Yochanan, כגון שגזל עצים משופין ועשאן
כלים, k'gon shegazal eitzim meshupin va'asan keilim, דהוי ליה שינוי החוזר לברייתו.
d'havei lei shinuy hachozer livriyaso. No no no. Rabbi Yochanan never said
anything that radical. Sure, of course Rabbi Yochanan agrees that the תורה
Torah recognizes a שינוי. shinuy. And if you went there and you
took lumber and you banged it and you and you know and
you took wood and nails and whatever and you turned it into
a table, of course from the תורה Torah הלכה halacha you don't
have to give it back. What he means that from the תורה
Torah you would have to give it back and the rabbis say
you wouldn't is what we talked about yesterday, a שינוי שחוזר לברייתו.
shinuy shechozer livriyaso. You stole a type of a thing and you
made you you know you put pieces of wood together without using
one nail and you just fitted them together in a way that
you could take it apart. Okay so in a way that's reversible,
that he says according to the תורה Torah you're לא קנה, lo
koneh, but the חכמים Chachamim say you're קונה koneh in order for
תקנת השבים. takanas hashavim. Okay but of course a real שינוי, shinuy,
that we're not going to debate, that even according to the תורה
Torah the תורה Torah recognizes and that you own. Okay so now
we have a full שינוי, shinuy, where are we now? We have
a full שינוי, shinuy, that a radical change, not חוזר לברייתו chozer
livriyaso etc. where it sounds like, you know, everybody holds in principle
that's קונה, koneh, although you have some cases where there might be
some like exceptions in certain local cases, like תזבח יתירה tizbach yeseira
or אתנן esnan or מצוה הבאה בעבירה, mitzvah haba'ah b'aveirah, okay, so
that's like once, but in principle everyone holds by it. But then
the question is what constitutes a שינוי? shinuy? People have different standards,
right? Is dyeing something if it could be removed by is that
considered חוזר לברייתו? chozer livriyaso? In general if something has radically changed
but it's חוזר לברייתו, chozer livriyaso, is that considered a שינוי דאורייתא?
shinuy d'Oraisa? You know not דאורייתא d'Oraisa but yes דרבנן? d'Rabanan? You
know what you know so all these questions of exactly what the
standard is. But here we've introduced a new idea of תקנת השבים,
takanas hashavim, meaning yesterday we said that if it's חוזר לברייתו chozer
livriyaso it works it might be it doesn't work דאורייתא d'Oraisa but
it works דרבנן. d'Rabanan. But we didn't say the reason was a
תקנה, takanah, right, we just said maybe that's like a classic case
of the rabbis expanding a דאורייתא d'Oraisa concept. But here Rabbi Yochanan
is saying no no no, there's an active idea that you should
have to return it, we don't recognize the שינוי, shinuy, but in
order to excuse me that you should wait did I say that
right? Yes, you should have to return it, but in order to
make it easier for people for to address a societal issue we're
going to allow you to own it even though you should have
to return it.
So we're both saying the same thing though in terms of you
having it.
It's basically שינוי החוזר לברייתו shinuy hachozer livriyaso is a שינוי דרבנן,
shinuy d'Rabanan, but we're making it a שינוי דרבנן shinuy d'Rabanan because
of תקנת השבים. takanas hashavim. Right. תנו רבנן: Tanu rabanan: הגזלנים ומלוי
בריבית. Hagazlanim u'malvei b'ribis. Now people that are professional גזלנים gazlanim here,
okay, it's not like you stole one thing, you're a גזלן gazlan
or a somebody who lends with ריבית, ribis, שהחזירו, shehechiziru, if they
returned they're trying to now you know come forward and give back
the stuff that the money the interest they charged the stuff that
they stole, אין מקבלין מהן. ein mikablin mehen. You refuse to accept
it.
So he stole my car and I shouldn't get it back?
If somebody is a professional גזלן gazlan you should not take it
back. Why not? Let's take a look. והמקבל מהן, V'hamikabel mehen, and
if somebody who who says you know what I know I was
told not to take it back but come on it's my stuff
I want it back, אין רוח חכמים נוחה הימנו. ein ruach chachamim
nocha heimenu. The sages are not happy with you. Now by the
way that's normally how that's explained, the sages are not happy with
you. רש״י Rashi says it means the spirit of wisdom רוח חכמה
ruach chochmah does not dwell in your midst is not in you
know is not it's very interesting רש״י Rashi on that I just
noticed רש״י Rashi says if you look at רש״י, Rashi, רש״י Rashi
says אין רוח חכמים ein ruach chachamim it's about eight lines down
in the inner line
אין רוח חכמה.
ein ruach chochmah. So now let's take a look. This seems completely
bizarre. Okay, this isn't even with a שינוי.
shinuy. Okay, this seems like in all cases.
אמר רבי יוחנן: Amar Rabbi Yochanan: בימי רבי נשנית משנה זו. Bimei
Rabbi nishneit mishnah zu. This mishnah was taught in the time of
Rabbi. דתניא: Detanya: מעשה בבן אדם אחד שביקש לעשות תשובה. Maaseh beven
adam echad shebikesh laasot teshuvah. A certain person wanted to do תשובה.
teshuvah. אמרה לו אשתו, Amrah lo ishto, his wife said to him:
ריקה, Reika, empty person, idiot, אם אתה עושה תשובה, im atah oseh
teshuvah, you come to do תשובה, teshuvah, אפילו אבנטך שלך, afilu avnetekha
shelekha, we won't have anything left, even your belt is not yours,
everything we have here is stolen. ונמנע ולא עשה תשובה, Venimna velo
asah teshuvah, so he didn't do תשובה. teshuvah. באותה שעה אמרו: Beotah
sha'ah amru: הגזלנים ומלוי ריבית, hagazlanim umalveh ribit, those that steal and
and lend in ribbit, שהחזירו אין מקבלים מהם, she-heziru ein mekabelim me-hem,
you do not accept from them, וכל המקבל מהם אין רוח חכמים
נוחה הימנו. vechol hamekabel mehem ein ruach chachamim nocha heimenu. Now obviously
this means like, what are you kidding me? You mean to tell
me that you cannot take money back from גזלנים? gazlanim? And תוספות
Tosafot says: מעשה בכל יום, maaseh bechol yom, גזלן gazlan comes to
return money and we take it back. So תוספות Tosafot says two
answers. One answer is this only applied to the דור של רבי
dor shel Rabbi and not to any future generations, not before and
not after. Okay, that's alright, that's cute, but like it's still, like
it was still seems to have been a crazy תקנה takanah even
to be made in
the period of Rabbi. His other answer is it only applies to
professionals, meaning, and of course you could say it's ironic, it is
ironic, but if I steal one thing, of course, and I want
come to give it back or even I stole a few things,
you're going to take it from me. But the person for whom
the state's about אפילו אבנטך שלך, afilu avnetekha shelekha, right? So that
type of a person, this is getting in the way of them,
you know, it's like the consequence of the fact that we would
accept it would make it impossible because they'd have to just clean
out their entire bank account. Okay, so it's very ironic. Now of
course the question is does that mean you don't take the object
back but you can get compensation? Right? Because if if you're not
going to get compensated besides that it's not fair to you, the
question is why do I care about the guy's תשובה? teshuvah? Okay,
יישר כוח, yishar koach, he did תשובה, teshuvah, but he did תשובה
teshuvah and he didn't return and he didn't make good for one
lousy thing. Right? So meaning it's like besides that I don't even
care why, you know, is God going to give him, you know,
תשובה teshuvah for not having reverted it? It's like why is it
in a society's interest? Right? We don't make תקנות takanot in property
issues so that it could be better for you in your, you
know, between you and God. Right? We make it, if we're somebody
else is going to have to give up their financial interest or
whatever, it's because it's going to be better for society. What good
is this person's תשובה teshuvah going to be if nobody's getting compensated?
Okay, so it's a really hard to understand this. But if it's
only limited to the, the גמרא Gemara in a minute is going
to suggest it's only limited to the objects themselves. Compensation may be,
or if they stole money as opposed to the objects or whatever,
okay, we'll see in a minute in the, okay, no, I think
the גמרא Gemara does it in the reverse. Anyway, but I think
that that's an important question to ask, which is who cares about
the תשובה teshuvah if nobody's being helped by his bias. Okay, but
anyway but תוספות Tosafot at least says other than saying it was
only for that generation, תוספות Tosafot at least says that this at
least is limited and it's completely consistent with the cases in the
גמרא Gemara of somebody that is a professional where it would really
stand in the way because then they'd become have to give up
everything they own. Yeah, so
that's what it is. So, you know, so because of that, ונמנע
ולא עשה תשובה, venimna velo asah teshuvah, and he could have said
alright, so maybe just pay for it, you know, but it's, but
that's a pos- but we're going to see because it sounds and
whether whether paying for it is the alternative or whether they don't
give anything back. So let's take a look. Okay, מתיבי, mativei, I
ask on this: הניח להם אביהם מעות של ריבית, hiniach lahem avihem
maot shel ribit, if their father left them money of ריבית, ribit,
and this is again presuming according to that read of תוספות Tosafot
that their father was a מלווה בריבית. malveh beribit. So he left
with them money that he had taken in interest. אף על פי
שיודעים שהיא ריבית, af al pi she-yodim she-hi ribit, even if they
know that it was interest money, אין חייבים להחזיר, ein chayavim lehachazir,
they don't have to return it to the person who it was
taken from. This is very much a,
אינהו הוא דלא, inhu hu delo, so it is they don't have
to return it, אביהם חייב להחזיר, avihem chayav lehachazir, the father would
have to return it. So how does that work? If you said
that the person who's מלווה בריבית malveh beribit doesn't return the money?
So the גמרא Gemara says no: בדין הוא דאביהם נמי אינו חייב
להחזיר, bedin hu de-avihem nami eino chayav lehachazir, really the father doesn't
have to return it. Which is crazy, you know why? Because even
if there's a תקנה takanah that's saying you should not receive it,
to not be willing to say there's an obligation to return, how
radical we think this תקנת השבים takanat hashavim is that we think
that the ברייתא braita should not even say there's an obligation to
return, seems like crazy. Okay, anyway, but בדין הוא דאביהם נמי אינו
חייב להחזיר. bedin hu de-avihem nami eino chayav lehachazir. The father doesn't
have to after this
תקנה. takanah. והא דקתני בדידהו, veha diktani bedidehu, why does it say
they don't have to return it? משום דבעי למיתני
סיפא, mishum de-baei lemitnei seifa, we want to take the end of
this case: הניח להם אביהם פרה וטלית, hiniach lahem avihem parah vetallit,
let's say their father had stolen a cow or a טלית, tallit,
or he had received a cow or a טלית tallit as a
payment for ריבית. ribit. וכל דבר מסוים, vechol davar mesuyam, or anything
concrete, חייבים להחזיר מפני כבוד אביהם. chayavim lehachazir mipnei kevod avihem. So
there, they do have to return it. Even though you don't have
to return ריבית, ribit, they do have to return this because it's
a disgrace to their father that people see them going around with
a טלית... tallit... So therefore, תניא נמי בדידהו *tanya nami bididhu*. It
also said by them that they don't have to return it. But
actually in the case of them, but actually even the father himself
wouldn't have to return it because of תקנת השבים *takanas hashavim*. Now
by the way, I just want to pause for a moment, which
is this isn't really our focus, but say, this idea that the
kids don't have to return something their father stole, okay, is really,
might be, I mean we're going to have a whole פרק *perek*
about it later, but it might be specifically about ריבית *ribbis*, because
ריבית *ribbis* is very funny. ריבית *ribbis* is something that I have
a contractual obligation to pay you, right? But you aren't allowed to
obligate me to pay you or you've transgressed by doing it. But
when I actually pay you, is that money that you're now holding
onto my money or your money? If you steal it, it's my
money that you've stolen. If I give it to you in ריבית
*ribbis* payment, it might be your money that you transgressed, but still,
it was now at the end of the day, it still is
legally your money. So that could be why the kids, that obligation
to return ריבית *ribbis* might only be on the person who transgressed.
If I steal and I have an object that you know, if
somebody steals and they have an object that doesn't belong to them
and they die, of course the kids have an obligation to return
it. It's, right? It's not כבוד אביהם *kevod avihem*. If somebody steals
a car, he dies. The owner can come and take his car
back, right? But if it was a car given in a ריבית
*ribbis* payment, okay, then maybe it really does belong to the other
person and the only reason that the kids would have to give
it back is because of כבוד אביהם *kevod avihem*. So that's the
idea that's going on here by ריבית *ribbis*. But anyway, the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* is saying that if it was the father himself, he
also wouldn't have to give it back if it wasn't the, you
know, if it wasn't an embarrassment type of a thing, but it's
only because of תקנת השבים *takanas hashavim*. But let's talk about the
kids to deal with the case about giving back the cow and
the טלית *tallis*. Yes. So is this an application of not only
are you forbidden to charge me interest, I'm forbidden to pay you
interest? That is true, but I don't know how that's relevant for
this. But that would cause a different status than me simply having
that car stolen. Oh, I see, you're saying we both transgressed. That's
a good point. That's a nice point. Okay. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* digresses for a minute. ומפני כבוד אביהם חייבים להחזיר
*umipnei kevod avihem chayavim lehachazir*. Why do they have to, why do
they care about their father's honor? אקרי כאן ונשיא בעמך לא תאור
*ikrei kan venasi be'amcha lo sa'or*, a נשיא *nasi* in your nation
you should not curse. So we say בעמך *be'amcha* means בעושה מעשה
עמך *be'oseh ma'aseh amcha*. It's also play on the word נשיא עושה
*nasi oseh*... בעושה מעשה עמך *be'oseh ma'aseh amcha*. If he's acting like
one of your people. So if the father was, you know, was
the guy who lent with ריבית *ribbis*, the kids aren't obligated to
care about his honor. I don't understand why it's not also a
question about the kids' honor. People are going to see them walking
around with a ריבית *ribbis* cow anyway. תנא מרי בר פנחס בשעשה
תשובה teshuva. *tana Mari bar Pinchas beshe'asah teshuvah*. No, no, no, it
was a case he did תשובה teshuva, *teshuvah*. You see how well
that תקנת השבים *takanas hashavim* worked? It got him to do תשובה
teshuva *teshuvah*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*...
so that's why they have to care about their father's honor when
he leaves
them over a cow. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says הכי נמי בשעשה
תשובה teshuva. *hachi nami beshe'asah teshuvah*. So that's the case here. אי
עשה תשובה teshuva? מאי בעי גביה *ei asah teshuvah mai ba'i gabei*?
Why is the cow still with him? You know, why didn't the
cow get returned? Because we said you're not allowed to take a
cow... Anyway, but okay. The גמרא *Gemara* says מאי בעי גביה *mai
ba'i gabei*, איבעי ליה לאהדורי *iba'i lei le'ahadurei*, he should have returned
it. שלא הספיק להחזיר עד שמת *shelo hispik lehachazir ad shemes*. He
didn't get a chance to return it until he died. But you
know, again, what I was saying was only a little ironic. If
you're really telling me that you did a תקנת השבים *takanas hashavim*
and you can't accept it back, then the reason it's still with
him is because of, you know, your תקנת השבים *takanas hashavim*. Your
תקנת השבים *takanas hashavim* is crazy. You know, but okay, anyway, we've
got this idea that it sounds like obviously the פשט *pshat* of
this ברייתא *braisa* is the father would have to return under all
cases, and it's a question about the kids and them כבוד אביהם
*kevod avihem* and so on, whether the object is a concrete object
or not. But we're now saying that you never accept money back
from a professional גנב *ganav*, גזלן *gazlan*, or מלווה בריבית *malveh beribbis*,
so we have to say the father also you wouldn't accept it
back. Okay, let's do one more case. תא שמע ta shema: *ta
shema*, come and hear. הגזלנים והמלוי בריבית *hagezlanim vehamalveh beribbis*, you see
this read of תוספות *Tosafos* works very well, because here it really
is talking about professionals. תא שמע *ta shema* trying to prove whether
we made a תקנת השבים *takanas hashavim* to not take the money
back. אף על פי שגבו *af al pi shegavu*, even if they
collected their money, אין מחזירין *ein machzirin*. They still have to return
it. The גמרא *Gemara* just says the word גבו *gavu* only applies
to מלווה בריבית *malveh beribbis*. גזלני מאי שגבו איכא *gazlani mai shegavu
ika*? What do you mean that they collected by a גזלן *gazlan*?
אי גזל גזל *ei gazal gazal*, if he stole he stole, ואי
לא גזל לא גזל *ve'ei lo gazal lo gazal*, if he didn't
steal he didn't steal. But there's no collecting. אלא אימא *ela eima*,
here's how you read it. הגזלנין *hagezlanin*, thieves, and who are the
thieves? והם המלוי בריבית *vehem hamalveh beribbis*, people who lend with ריבית
*ribbis*. That gets back to that issue I discussed before. Do you
think somebody collecting interest, you look at him as stealing that money
or not? But anyway, אף על פי שגבו *af al pi shegavu*,
even after they collected the money, מחזירין *machzirin*, they have to return
it. So you see they return it, and you said that there
was a תקנה takana. *takanah* that you don't take it back. אמר
ליה מחזירין ואין מקבלין מהם *amar lei machzirin ve'ein mekabelin mehem*, which
is obviously what you would have to say even if you believe
in this תקנת השבים *takanas hashavim*. That they're supposed to return it.
You're not supposed to accept it. Okay? Because at least, right, that
at least explains, like, to say that, okay, nobody ever has to
return is crazy. But if you sort of say, now the dynamic
makes a little more sense with their תקנת השבים *takanas hashavim*. is
really more directed at the receiver, at the אין מקבלין ain mekabelin,
מהן. And that was the original statement, right? The original statement was
אין מקבלין, so now it makes sense. This guy is coming to
return. We advise you not to accept. Now you can choose, hey,
it's $1,000, I don't have a lot of money, thanks for the
advice rabbis, I'm taking it back. Okay, but we are advising people
not to accept to smooth the path to תשובה. teshuva So therefore
there will be some people who will forego it. And therefore it'll
be easier for them. There will be some people who won't, but
some people who will. And it also explains why it's a תשובה,
Teshuva 'cause he still has to come and try to return every
object. But to make it easier, we're telling the people, we advise
you to say no. Okay, so now the whole thing makes a
little bit more sense. Okay. מחזירין ואין מקבלין מהן. machzirin ve-ain mekabelin
meihen. אלא למה מחזירין? ella lamma machzirin? So why are they returning?
לצאת ידי שמים, latzeit yedei shamayim, 'cause they have to be trying
to do their real obligation vis-a-vis heaven. Otherwise what type of תשובה
teshuva it is? And I would also add because then it also
allows some people to agree to accept. It might be אינו מחכמים
נוחה, aino mei-chachamim nocha, but at least you could agree. Okay, so
let's just read one more case because this is very important because
it gives some qualification to what we're saying. תא שמע: הרועים והגבאים,
ha-roim ve-ha-gabbaim, shepherds and גבאים gabbaim which are type of tax collectors.
מוכסים mochsin are different type of tax collectors. תשובתן קשה. teshuvatan kasha.
So they steal because they overcharge in their taxes and the shepherds
go to maybe other fields. Very hard for them to do תשובה.
teshuva You know why it's hard for them to do תשובה? teshuva
'Cause they stole from too many people. And they don't know who
they stole from. They stole from so many people, they don't even
know who. Okay. תשובתן קשה. teshuvatan kasha. ומחזירין למכירין. u-machzirin le-makirin. They
give back the money to the people that they know they stolen
from. Okay. Now what they do to the people they don't know
they stolen from we'll talk about in a minute. But anyway, you
see, they give it back. And presumably the people accept it. So
the גמרא says no. אמי מחזירין ואין מקבלין מהן. ami machzirin ve-ain
mekabelin meihen. Yeah, they try to give it back, but the people
should not accept it. So the גמרא says אלא למה מחזירין? ella
lamma machzirin? So why are they giving back? לצאת ידי שמים. latzeit
yedei shamayim. אי הכי, ei hachi, if that's true, אמי תשובתן קשה?
ami teshuvatan kasha? Why is their תשובה so difficult? תשובה is very
easy. I'm just saying I'm giving back to anybody and everybody has
to say no. והא איכא סיפא, ve-ha ika seifa, look at the
end. ומה שאין מכירין, u-ma she-ain makirin, those they don't know, יעשה
בהן צרכי ציבור. ya'aseh ba-hen tzorchei tzibbur. What they have to do
is they have to make some contribution to the community. They have
to build a well or something, as we're going to say. אמר
רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, בורות שיחין ומערות, borot shichin u-mearot, let
them build wells and cisterns, stay in put money that that benefits
the entire community. אלא לא קשיא: Ella lo kashya: כאן קודם תקנה
כאן לאחר תקנה. kan kodem takana kan le-achar takana. Okay. Ah, no,
you know what? That was talking about before the תקנה. takana Before
the תקנה takana. we would accept it and they would have and
then their תשובה would be difficult. Now we're talking about after the
תקנה. takana Okay. So we're going to end here. The גמרא is
going to continue to figure out how far this תקנה takana reaches.
But now we are saying that this תקנה takana. applies to professionals
and at least what the גמרא is sort of saying at the
end is it doesn't mean they're not obligated to return. They're obligated
to return but everybody is told not to accept it. Okay? Which
creates at least a dynamic which could make some degree of sense
of how they could be doing their תשובה and why the תשובה
would be meaningful and why we would have this type of a
תקנה. This came up a lot in the you know with milk
and stuff like that.